<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<title>thomas ohashi / blog</title>
	<id>http://www.thomasohashi.com/</id>
	<link href="https://www.thomasohashi.com" rel="alternate"/>
	<link href="https://www.thomasohashi.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
	<updated>2025-02-14T14:26:55-08:00</updated>
	<author>
		<name>Thomas Ohashi</name>
	</author>
	<entry>
		<title>Cool Game: Formless Star</title>
		<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.thomasohashi.com/blog/cool-game-formless-star.html"/>
		<id>https://www.thomasohashi.com/blog/cool-game-formless-star.html</id>
		<published>2025-06-01T13:08:06-07:00</published>
		<updated>2025-06-02T09:59:19-07:00</updated>
		<content>
			<![CDATA[
				<p>Hot on the heels of my <em>Franken</em> recommendation is a new game by Splendidland, <a href="https://splendidland.itch.io/formless-star"><em>Formless Star</em></a>, a short and lovely JRPG style game taking pretty direct inspiration from the relatively recently localized PlayStation game <em>Moon</em> (which is also great).</p>
				
				<p>You play as a member of a crew that was hired by a space cartographer to document an endlessly changing planet by finding and identifying all of the animals that live there. The way you do this is by wandering around the map through its various biomes and interacting with anything interesting. If you get stuck or run out of places to look you can teleport back to your ship and go inside. When you go back outside the planet will have reformed itself.</p>
				
				<p>Each area looks incredible and you can easily clear obstacles or build bridges, so wandering around is a fun and relaxing experience.</p>
				
				<figure>
				<img src="/blog/images/cool-games/formless-star/Splendidland-1.png" alt="Screenshot from Formless Star: The player character, who has an apple-like head, stands in the middle of the screen surrounded by fruit and gummy land tiles, some flower and grass land tiles, and some water tiles" />
				</figure>
				
				<p>The animal designs and their interactions are all pretty great. I don’t want to spoil much so I’m only going to share a screenshot of #1.</p>
				
				<figure>
				<img src="/blog/images/cool-games/formless-star/Splendidland-2.png" alt="Screenshot from Formless Star: The player stands next to a long necked quadruped animal with white and red stripes and a head shaped like the top of a lighthouse. There is a UI encyclopedia menu that shows the animal on a grid and a text entry that reads: #01: Lighthorse - Stands at the coastline to act as a beacon, however it has difficulty discerning a puddle from an ocean. Said to be proud of its red stripes." />
				</figure>
				
				<p>The writing is really nice and thoughtful too. I’m not going to go as far as to say this game is good for your mental health because I’m not a doctor, but it might be, so do yourself a favor and try it out.</p>
			]]>
		</content>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<title>Cool Game: Franken</title>
		<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.thomasohashi.com/blog/cool-game-franken.html"/>
		<id>https://www.thomasohashi.com/blog/cool-game-franken.html</id>
		<published>2025-05-25T12:59:33-07:00</published>
		<updated>2025-05-25T12:59:33-07:00</updated>
		<content>
			<![CDATA[
				<p>Wow, another post already. Well, this one will probably be quick.</p>
				
				<p>I just played <a href="https://splendidland.itch.io/franken">Franken</a> and if you are a fan of RPGs and/or humor then I think you should give it a shot too.</p>
				
				<p>Franken sits somewhere in the post Undertale and/or inspired by Earthbound and/or Moon and definitely parodying SNES RPGs in particular FFIV realm. I guess that’s very specific but it’s more about the general vibe if you like <em>any</em> of those games mentioned then you will probably find this amusing.</p>
				
				<p>It’s quite short, maybe an hour total, but it’s filled with good jokes and good vibes. I started playing 1000xRESIST and after two chapters I felt like I needed something to lift my spirits and this did just that.</p>
				
				<p>The art is also just fantastic. Behold:</p>
				
				<img src="/blog/images/cool-games/franken/franken-fountain.png" alt="Screenshot from Franken. An old man named Elder stands next to a very simple pixel art water tile and says this exquisite ornate fountain is the pride of our town." />
				
				<p>Seriously though it’s actually very nice. I foolishly didn’t take any of my own screenshots but all of the characters and enemies look great and I don’t want to spoil them anyway so go check the game out already!</p>
			]]>
		</content>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<title>Cool Music: HONEYPAQQ Vol. 1 by HiTech</title>
		<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.thomasohashi.com/blog/cool-music-honeypaqq-vol-1.html"/>
		<id>https://www.thomasohashi.com/blog/cool-music-honeypaqq-vol-1.html</id>
		<published>2025-05-23T14:15:33-07:00</published>
		<updated>2025-05-23T14:15:33-07:00</updated>
		<content>
			<![CDATA[
				<p>For a while I’ve been wanting to blog more but I don’t feel like I have enough to say most of the time. I do spend a lot of time looking for cool new things though, so maybe it’s fine to just post about what I find and like. I’m going to try my best to not be too self conscious about my ability to write critically about things and just write what comes naturally. I hope some of you find it interesting!</p>
				
				<p>My favorite new album this month, and one of my favorites of 2025 so far, is <a href="https://hitechdetroit.bandcamp.com/album/honeypaqq-vol-1">HONEYPAQQ Vol. 1</a> by HiTech. I really enjoyed their 2023 album <a href="https://hitechdetroit.bandcamp.com/album/d-twat">DÉTWAT</a> for its fun and frenetic house beats with <a href="https://hitechdetroit.bandcamp.com/track/pocketpussy">hilariously raunchy lyrics</a> and HONEYPAQQ Vol. 1 is a terrific followup.</p>
				
				<p>I am historically not much of a dancer but I’ve been trying to relax my inhibitions around that and sometimes hearing the right song makes it so much easier. The first time I heard NEW JAZZ SCHMELL I couldn’t help but start to dance at my desk and I proceeded to replay it like five times. The groove is too powerful.</p>
				
				<iframe style="border: 0; width: 100%; height: 120px;" src="https://bandcamp.com/EmbeddedPlayer/album=1983664209/size=large/bgcol=ffffff/linkcol=0687f5/tracklist=false/artwork=small/track=2080504133/transparent=true/" seamless><a href="https://hitechdetroit.bandcamp.com/album/honeypaqq-vol-1">Cool Music: HONEYPAQQ Vol. 1 by HiTech</a></iframe>
				
				<p>Another standout track is SHADOWREALM featuring one of my favorite working rappers Zelooperz. It’s just fun and hype as hell.</p>
				
				<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/l0A_IDof5Dk?si=d2nswjCwxGNCSrVT" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe>
				
				<p>After a long period of mostly listening to rap and synthwave I’ve been having a lot of fun discovering new (to me) electronic genres like dungeonsynth as well as rekindling my love for genres I used to listen to like house and drum &amp; bass.</p>
				
				<p>HiTech falls somewhere in the middle of that for me. The Chicago house origins feel familiar while the high energy techno aspects feels really fresh, even if the style itself has been around for a long time. I picked out a couple favorites but I think the whole album is pretty great and I hope some of you enjoy it too.</p>
			]]>
		</content>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<title>Fake video game soundtracks</title>
		<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.thomasohashi.com/blog/fake-video-game-soundtracks.html"/>
		<id>https://www.thomasohashi.com/blog/fake-video-game-soundtracks.html</id>
		<published>2025-03-24T14:48:31-07:00</published>
		<updated>2025-03-24T14:51:57-07:00</updated>
		<content>
			<![CDATA[
				<p>In recent years I have found that when I am working on something I can no longer listen to music with lyrics. Words are too distracting but I still want to enjoy what I’m listening to instead of putting on some random “beats to study to” playlist or weird algorithmic focus music. I play a lot of video games and you might think that there’s a wealth of albums to listen to there, but for me that isn’t really the case.</p>
				
				<p>While there are a lot of video game soundtracks that I love, there are very few that I would choose to listen to outside the context of their game (shout out <a href="https://garoad.bandcamp.com/album/va-11-hall-a-second-round">VA-11 Hall-A</a> and <a href="https://kaizengameworks.bandcamp.com/album/paradise-killer-original-soundtrack">Paradise Killer</a>). When each song is specifically designed to suit a particular location or scene you get great geographical and emotional range, but when listened to back to back the abrupt transitions you end up with between songs can create serious tonal whiplash. On top of that, songs like <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cvCn6FNnYyI"><em>It Happened Late One Evening</em></a> from <em>Secret of Mana</em> or <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0U2EyeE0n88"><em>Tonoe de Pon</em></a> from <em>Phantasy Star IV</em> are passable in their respective games (actually, maybe not so much <em>Tonoe de Pon</em>) but absolutely not something I would choose to listen to otherwise.</p>
				
				<p>Fortunately, some cool electronic artists have come up with a solution. Please give it up for fake video game soundtracks.</p>
				
				<p>Since there’s no actual game the artists are free to arrange songs in a way that feels natural while still covering a wide range of soundscapes should they choose to do so. If you have never heard a video game soundtrack before then you might not really connect with these in the same way, but I think the narrative journey they take you on could still resonate.</p>
				
				<img src="/blog/images/fakevideogamesoundtracks/Equip-Palace.png" alt="Album art: Equip - I Dreamed of a Palace in the Sky" />
				
				<p>The first one I found was <a href="https://worldofequip.bandcamp.com/album/i-dreamed-of-a-palace-in-the-sky"><em>I Dreamed of a Palace in the Sky</em></a>, released by the electronic musician <a href="https://worldofequip.bandcamp.com/">Equip</a> in 2016. Taking inspiration from 16-bit RPGs and vaporwave, Equip created an album with the adventurous spirit and progression of a SNES RPG soundtrack but with much more deliberate sequencing so it’s pleasant to listen to from start to finish. As one might expect from the vaporwave influence, it’s a pretty chill album and makes for great background music.</p>
				
				<img src="/blog/images/fakevideogamesoundtracks/Equip&R23X-NamelessDreamers.png" alt="Album art: Equip & R23X - Nameless Dreamers" />
				
				<p>I had actually forgotten about this album for years until another Equip release popped up on my radar, this time a collaborative album released in 2022 called <a href="https://worldofequip.bandcamp.com/album/nameless-dreamers-2"><em>Nameless Dreamers</em></a> with an artist called <a href="https://r23x.bandcamp.com/">R23X</a>. For me, <em>Nameless Dreamers</em> hits the nostalgia notes harder and at times it’s almost uncanny how much it sounds like I’m listening to lost songs from <em>Chrono Trigger</em>, <em>A Link to the Past</em>, or <em>Final Fantasy VI</em>. The sporadic menu and battle sound samples really help sell it.</p>
				
				<img src="/blog/images/fakevideogamesoundtracks/LeonChang-ReturnToBirdWorld.png" alt="Album art: Return to Bird World" />
				
				<p>Around the same time I came across <a href="https://leyawn.bandcamp.com">Leon Chang</a>’s 2017 album <a href="https://leyawn.bandcamp.com/album/bird-world"><em>bird world</em></a> and its 2020 sequel <a href="https://leyawn.bandcamp.com/album/return-to-bird-world"><em>return to bird world</em></a>. It feels like there’s a lot of Nintendo influence in Leon Chang’s work, with whimsy that makes me think more of <em>Super Mario RPG</em> than of <em>Final Fantasy</em>. Some of Leon’s tracks would fit perfectly <em>in</em> a game while others tend to sound a bit more <em>inspired by</em> games, with strong melodies that have a little too much presence for soundtrack music, but that are nonetheless great for background music in normal life.</p>
				
				<img src="/blog/images/fakevideogamesoundtracks/MitchMurder-PitStopHero.png" alt="Album art: Mitch Murder - Pit Stop Hero" />
				
				<p>Deviating from the RPG formula is a more recent Leon Chang release called <a href="https://leyawn.bandcamp.com/album/leon-kart"><em>Leon Kart</em></a>, inspired by <em>Mario Kart</em>, which dovetails nicely with some newer work by another electronic artist I like called <a href="https://mitchmurder.bandcamp.com/">Mitch Murder</a>. Recently he has dabbled in 32-bit racing game inspired soundtracks like <a href="https://mitchmurder.bandcamp.com/album/pit-stop-hero-ost"><em>Pit Stop Hero</em></a>, released in 2023, which purports to be from a Sega Saturn F-1 racing game, and <a href="https://wereleasewhateverthefuckwewantrecords.bandcamp.com/album/anti-gravity-tournament"><em>Anti Gravity Tournament</em></a>, a collaborative album with the artist <a href="https://pizzahotline.bandcamp.com/">Pizza Hotline</a> released late 2024, that is heavily inspired by <em>Wipeout</em>.</p>
				
				<img src="/blog/images/fakevideogamesoundtracks/HelloMeteor-OahuGP2.png" alt="Album art: Hello Meteor - The Oahu GP 2 Hyper Tropic" />
				
				<p>In a similar vein, <a href="https://hellometeor.bandcamp.com/">Hello Meteor</a> has released two PlayStation/Saturn era racing game inspired soundtracks of his own, <a href="https://hellometeor.bandcamp.com/album/the-oahu-gp"><em>The Oahu GP</em></a> in 2021 and <a href="https://hellometeor.bandcamp.com/album/the-oahu-gp-2-hyper-tropic"><em>The Oahu GP 2: Hyper Tropic</em></a> in 2024. Compared to the RPG inspired soundtracks these racing game albums are faster and more upbeat, featuring fun breakbeats inspired by jungle, house, trap, and drum & bass, but they still have some sense of progression and escalation between songs as races get more intense or locations change, and in some cases there are even opening, menu, and failure tracks to round things out.</p>
				
				<img src="/blog/images/fakevideogamesoundtracks/FMSkyline&Equip-Music2.png" alt="FM Skyline & Equip - Music 2" />
				
				<p>Circling back to Equip, his newest release is another collaboration called <a href="https://fmskyline.bandcamp.com/album/music-2"><em>Music 2</em></a>, released this year with the artist <a href="https://fmskyline.bandcamp.com/">FM Skyline</a>. Both artists heavily incorporate nostalgia into their work and this album feels less like a specific game soundtrack than an attempt to capture a particular vibe. Listening to it, I hear <em>Ape Escape</em>, <em>Panzer Dragoon Saga</em>, and <em>Ridge Racer</em>, among other influences, but with funkier breakbeats and more vaporwave. I’m almost more inclined to just call this a good electronic album, but I think it still deserves a place somewhere on this spectrum.</p>
				
				<img src="/blog/images/fakevideogamesoundtracks/BubbleBlade-VaporousHalls.png" alt="Album art: Bubble Blade - Vaporous Halls" />
				
				<p>Last but not least is a personal favorite that I stumbled upon mostly by accident, <a href="https://bubbleblade.bandcamp.com">Bubble Blade</a> AKA <a href="https://grimfather.bandcamp.com">Grimfather</a>. While I was looking for more fake video game soundtracks I also found dungeonsynth, which could be a whole other post, and Bubble Blade immediately caught my eye as a video game looking thing. Like a lot of dungeonsynth Bubble Blade has a slightly more sinister vibe, but <em>unlike</em> most dungensynth it has much a harder electronic edge. Both 2024’s <a href="https://bubbleblade.bandcamp.com/album/vaporous-halls"><em>Vaporous Halls</em></a> and the newly released <a href="https://bubbleblade.bandcamp.com/album/acid-path"><em>Acid Path</em></a> have an adventurous dungeon crawling spirit but with more reverb and much harder breaks. I had the pleasure of seeing Grimfather live and let me tell you, some of these songs go hard. It’s still RPG music but it kind of makes you want to dance too.</p>
				
				<img src="/blog/images/fakevideogamesoundtracks/LenaRaine-Earthblade.png" alt="Album art: Lena Raine - EARTHBLADE ~ Across the Bounds of Fate" />
				
				<p>I also want to give an honorable mention to <a href="https://radicaldreamland.bandcamp.com/album/earthblade-across-the-bounds-of-fate">Lena Raine</a>’s soundtrack for <a href="https://radicaldreamland.bandcamp.com/album/earthblade-across-the-bounds-of-fate"><em>Earthblade</em></a>, a game that we will sadly never play. I’m not sure how many of the songs were designed for a level that actually existed but it’s repackaged in a way that feels very deliberate as an auditory experience.</p>
				
				<p>It still surprises how few of these albums seem to exist. It’s probably a pretty niche format so maybe it’ll never really take off, and plenty of people are likely satisfied with existing video game soundtracks, but I think there’s something special about one that’s made specifically with listening in mind. If you know of any others please share them with me at contact (at) thomasohashi (dot) com!</p>
			]]>
		</content>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<title>Five years</title>
		<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.thomasohashi.com/blog/five-years.html"/>
		<id>https://www.thomasohashi.com/blog/five-years.html</id>
		<published>2025-03-06T17:26:18+00:00</published>
		<updated>2025-03-06T17:26:18+00:00</updated>
		<content>
			<![CDATA[
				<p>I was going to write a longer post about this but after several paragraphs I had barely scratched the surface and honestly I’m not sure I really want to relive that much of the experience anyway, so here’s an abridged version:</p>
				
				<ul>
					<li>In the summer of 2019 I was diagnosed with cancer in my lung via a routine x-ray as part of an annual health exam while living in Japan. I had no other symptoms</li>
					<li>The initial diagnosis was lung cancer but a biopsy ultimately proved it to be Hodgkin’s lymphoma, a much more treatable disease</li>
					<li>After some deliberation my partner and I decided to return to the US to undergo treatment, which was only possible thanks to the Oregon Health Plan</li>
					<li>I started treatment at OHSU in the fall and my last chemotherapy infusion was on Valentine’s Day (February 14th) in 2020</li>
					<li>On March 6th, 2020 I was told I was officially “in remission”</li>
					<li>I now have been in remission for five years</li>
				</ul>
				
				<p>To put it simply, it was very hard. It is still hard sometimes and it probably always will be. Since I never had any symptoms to begin with it has been difficult to fully believe that I am “cured”, which isn’t really what remission means anyway. There’s just no <em>evidence</em> of disease left.</p>
				
				<p>Whenever I have a new mystery symptom my first thought is inevitably “is this cancer”? Nevertheless, five years is a statistically meaningful milestone, and I have already lived much longer than I thought I was going to per my initial, fortunately inaccurate diagnosis. I am so, so grateful to be alive.</p>
				
				<p>Thank you to the nurses, doctors, and other medical staff who treated me, to my friends, family, and coworkers who supported me, and of course to Medicaid for allowing me to go through treatment at home.</p>
				<p>I wouldn't be here without you.</p>
			]]>
		</content>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<title>Kenny Dennis beginner's guide</title>
		<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.thomasohashi.com/blog/kenny-dennis-beginners-guide.html"/>
		<id>https://www.thomasohashi.com/blog/kenny-dennis-beginners-guide.html</id>
		<published>2025-02-25T00:20:16+00:00</published>
		<updated>2025-02-25T01:06:11+00:00</updated>
		<content type="html">
			<![CDATA[
			<h2>Kenny Dennis beginner's guide</h2>
				<h3>Who is Kenny Dennis?</h3>
				<p>Serengeti one of my favorite rappers, in no small part due to the epic body of work he has created around his alter ego Kenny Dennis.</p>
				<p>Kenny (formerly known as KDz) is a rapper from Chicago who was part of an upcoming group in the early 90s called Tha Grimm Teachaz. An unfortunate altercation with Shaquille O'Neal resulted in the group being dropped from their label and blacklisted, dooming Kenny to obscurity.</p>
				<p>What begins as a goofy comedy rap concept gradually becomes something more profound. Things don't always go well for Serengeti's characters and while their actions may be absurd their struggles feel tragic and real.</p>
				<p>For a more in depth overview there's a great <a href="https://daily.bandcamp.com/features/serengeti-kenny-dennis-feature">breakdown</a> on Bandcamp but it only covers through <em>Dennis 6e</em>, which at the time was intended to be the final album. Since then Serengti has both created albums for a new character in the same universe and released more Kenny Dennis albums.</p>
				<h3>Where should I start?</h3>
				<p>Well, somewhat counterintuitively, unless you're already sold on the idea I would recommend skipping ahead and starting with Ajai. The concept is more straightforward and Serengeti's writing at this point is near peak. Ajai is a hopeless hypebeast married to a doctor and his clothing addiction is negatively impacting their relationship. Kenny is featured throughout the album but his history isn't particularly important to Ajai's story.</p>
				<p>If you find yourself enjoying that then I think it'd be worth going back and at least skipping through some of the early Kenny stuff before getting started with <em>Kenny Dennis III</em>.
				<hr />
			<h2>Prehistory</h2>
				<h3>0. <a href="https://othar.bandcamp.com/album/theres-a-situation-on-the-homefront">Tha Grimm Teachaz - There’s a Situation on the Homefront</a></h3>
					<img src="/blog/images/kennydennis/grimmteachaz-theresasituation.jpg" alt="Tha Grimm Teachaz - There's a Situation on the Homefront album cover" />
					<p>This album, fictionally released in 1993, is a prequel to the Kenny Dennis anthology and features him rapping as KDz in the group Tha Grimm Teachaz. I think it's a pretty amazing parody of that era of hip-hop and all of KDz's verses are great but it's not the most narratively important album.</p>
				<hr />
			<h2>Origin</h2>
				<h3>1. <a href="https://fakefour.bandcamp.com/album/dennehy-w-beautyman-ep">Dennehy</a></h3>
					<img src="/blog/images/kennydennis/serengeti-dennehy.jpg" alt="Serengeti - Dennehy album cover" />
					<p>The first chronological appearance of Kenny Dennis. There's not really a story yet and only a few of the tracks on this album feature Kenny. <em>Dennehy</em> is probably the only "essential" song on here but <em>Don't talk to Jueles</em>, <em>New Dodge</em>, and <em>Ozzie Guillen</em> all expand on his character.</p>
				<hr />
				<h3>2. <a href="https://kennydennis.bandcamp.com/album/kenny-dennis-ep"> Kenny Dennis EP/Kenny Dennis and Perculators</a></h3>
					<img src="/blog/images/kennydennis/serengeti-kennydennis-ep.jpg" alt="Serengeti - Kenny Dennis EP album cover" />
					<p>The first full Kenny Dennis EP. Like <em>Dennehy</em>, there's more character building than narrative but it starts to flesh out his history, including his beef with Shaq through the amazing diss track <em>Shazam</em>. There is also a very silly riff on <em>Top That</em> from <em>Teen Witch</em>.</p>
				<hr />
			<h2>Chicago Era</h2>
				<h3>3. Kenny Dennis LP</h3>
					<img src="/blog/images/kennydennis/serengeti-kennydennis-lp.jpg" alt="Serengeti - Kenny Dennis III album cover" />
					<p>The story really kicks into gear here with the introduction of Ders, Kenny's longtime friend, occasional collaborator, and our documentary style narrator. <em>Directions</em> is one of my all time favorite KD songs but from this point on it's worth listening to everything.</p>
					<p>For some reason this album isn't on Bandcamp, but it is on streaming.</p>
				<hr />
				<h3>4. <a href="https://serengeti.bandcamp.com/album/kenny-dennis-iii">Kenny Dennis III</a></h3>
					<img src="/blog/images/kennydennis/serengeti-kennydennis-iii.jpg" alt="Serengeti - Kenny Dennis III album cover" />
					<p>There's more story to spoil from this point on so I'm going to keep my descriptions brief.</p>
					<p>Ders' narration continues, following his and Kenny's foray into music as Perfecto.</p>
				<hr />
				<h3>5. <a href="https://serengeti.bandcamp.com/album/you-cant-run-from-the-rhythm">Perfecto - You Can’t Run from the Rhythm</a></h3>
					<img src="/blog/images/kennydennis/perfecto-youcantrun.jpg" alt="Perfecto - You Can't Run from the Rhythm album cover" />
					<p>Serengeti made a Perfecto album to go with <em>Kenny Dennis III</em>.</p>
				<hr />
				<h3>6. <a href="https://kennydennis.bandcamp.com/album/jueles-butterflies">Jueles - Butterflies</a></h3>
					<img src="/blog/images/kennydennis/jueles-butterflies.jpg" alt="Jueles - Butterflies album cover" />
					<p>Between Jueles' upbeat dance tracks things start to break down with Kenny and Jueles.</p>
				<hr />
				<h3>7. <a href="https://kennydennis.bandcamp.com/album/dennis-6e">Dennis 6e</a></h3>
					<img src="/blog/images/kennydennis/serengeti-dennis6e.jpg" alt="Serengeti - Dennis 6e album cover" />
					<p>Kenny struggles with grief.</p>
				<hr />
			<h2>Minnesota Era</h2>
				<h3>8. <a href="https://kennydennis.bandcamp.com/album/ajai">Ajai</a></h3>
					<img src="/blog/images/kennydennis/serengeti-ajai.jpg" alt="Serengeti - Ajai album cover" />
					<p>We meet Ajai and catch up with Kenny in Minneapolis.</p>
				<hr />
				<h3>9. <a href="https://kennydennis.bandcamp.com/album/ajai-epilogue">Ajai Epilogue</a></h3>
					<img src="/blog/images/kennydennis/serengeti-ajai-epilogue.jpg" alt="Serengeti - Ajai Epilogue album cover" />
					<p>Things aren't going well with Ajai.</p>
				<hr />
				<h3>10. <a href="https://kennydennis.bandcamp.com/album/kdxmpc">KDxMPC</a></h3>
					<img src="/blog/images/kennydennis/serengeti-kdxmpc.jpg" alt="Serengeti - KDxMPC album cover" />
					<p>A Kenny Dennis interlude during Ajai's story.</p>
				<hr />
				<h3>11. <a href="https://kennydennis.bandcamp.com/album/ajai-ii">Ajai II</a></h3>
					<img src="/blog/images/kennydennis/serengeti-ajai-ii.jpg" alt="Serengeti - Ajai II album cover" />
					<p>Ajai struggles with his new life.</p>
				<hr />
				<h3>12. <a href="https://kennydennis.bandcamp.com/album/kenny-dennis-iv">KDIV</a></h3>
					<img src="/blog/images/kennydennis/serengeti-kdiv.jpg" alt="Serengeti - KDIV album cover" />
					<p>Kenny opens up during a long awaited reunion with and Ders.</p>
			]]>
		</content>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<title>I guess I'm a La-Mulana person now</title>
		<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.thomasohashi.com/blog/i-guess-im-a-la-mulana-person-now.html"/>
		<id>https://www.thomasohashi.com/blog/i-guess-im-a-la-mulana-person-now.html</id>
		<published>2025-02-14T14:26:55-08:00</published>
		<updated>2025-02-14T14:26:55-08:00</updated>
		<content type="html">
			<![CDATA[
			<h3>Prologue: Barbuta </h3>
			
			<p>It all started with <em>UFO 50</em>, or more specifically, with <em>Barbuta</em>.</p>
			
			<p><em>Barbuta</em> is chronologically the first game in <em>UFO 50</em> and seems to be very polarizing. The game feels quite hostile towards the player with its surprise traps, numerous hazards, erratic enemy movement, and awkward controls. There is also no music.</p>
			
			<p>That said, if you manage to persevere and dive deeper into the game you will find an elegant and meticulously crafted puzzle box — one that I found almost as satisfying to solve as Outer Wilds. I don’t want to spoil too much of the game but you might experience something like this:</p>
			
			<ul>
			<li>How do I get that?</li>
			<li>Oh that’s how I get it.</li>
			<li>What does it do?</li>
			<li>Oh it does that.</li>
			<li>Oh wow, I can also get it this way.</li>
			<li>Wait, do I even need to do that???</li>
			</ul>
			
			<p>And so on. Like <em>Outer Wilds</em> you could maybe call this game a metroidbrainia. There are no persistent upgrades but following different routes will yield new information that you will then go on to use to find even more routes until you finally understand how to complete the game. I loved it.</p>
			
			<p>After finishing the game I found out that the designer is a big fan of the game <em>La-Mulana</em>, which I had always assumed to be something of a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kaizo">kaizo</a> style game, but riding the high of <em>Barbuta</em> I figured I would give it a shot. It took many hours and extensive use of a guide but in the end, <em>La-Mulana</em> rewired my brain.</p>
			
			<h3>La-Mulana</h3>
			
			<p>Like <em>Barbuta</em>, <em>La-Mulana</em> is filled with traps and your movement is kind of awkward, but the game is surprisingly generous in many ways. Most fundamental is that you can save your game, which is pretty important considering the game is absolutely massive. Once you get the hang of the controls it is actually quite easy to avoid enemies, and assuming you find the item in the first area, you can access fast travel whenever you want! You also have a proper life bar that you can increase, so it is much easier to stay alive. That does not however, make it an easier game.</p>
			
			<p>Some of the bosses are admittedly pretty bad and there are some relatively frustrating platforming areas, but the real challenge is solving all of the puzzles. There are countless tablets with vague references to such and such or so and so and it turns out that most of them are hints to a puzzle somewhere, which you may not come across for dozens of hours. I foolishly thought I could keep it straight in my head but I couldn’t have been more wrong. Fortunately someone called Cheshire_1 on Steam made an amazing <a href="https://steamcommunity.com/sharedfiles/filedetails/?id=377234096">hint based guide</a>.</p>
			
			<p>I had a fantastic 15 hours where I felt like I was mostly solving things while occasionally looking up hints in the guide. Finding puzzles and solutions felt incredible and discovering new secrets about areas I had already been through was pleasantly mind-blowing. Unfortunately the puzzles went much deeper than that, and for the subsequent 15 hours I transitioned from referencing the guide as needed to completely following it and still feeling confused. What Nigoro has done with <em>La-Mulana</em> is legitimately remarkable but some of the puzzles are so obtuse that beating the game without a guide is basically <a href="https://youtu.be/C--iYdADbLo?si=ej5dziFdZAijqe7V">impossible</a>. The last big puzzle is so ridiculous that even with a guide I found it kind of infuriating.</p>
			
			<p>In spite of all that, I still cherish my time with <em>La-Mulana</em>. It’s a little hard to put into words but it ended up becoming a “place” I enjoyed spending time in, something that only rarely happens when I am genuinely, fully absorbed in something. Other examples for me would be <em>Breath of the Wild</em> and <em>Earthbound</em>, not coincidentally my two favorite games. The first half of <em>La-Mulana</em> alone is almost enough to place it amongst them, but the second half drags it down a notch or two. Fortunately there is a sequel that so far seems to have a more fair but no less impressive design...</p>
			
			<h3>Epilogue: Animal Well</h3>
			
			<p>If I have any regrets, it’s that I played <em>La-Mulana</em> before <em>Animal Well</em>, which I did enjoy but felt rather underwhelmed by in comparison. I think <em>La-Mulana</em> is more successful at gradually encouraging the player to engage with increasingly complicated puzzles while <em>Animal Well</em> provides you with a charming but fairly straightforward base game, then follows it with an abrupt pixel hunt before you can even really get started with the more complicated puzzles.</p>
			
			<p>Moving around also felt more tedious in <em>Animal Well</em> due to a less convenient fast travel system and the fussiness (IMO) of some of the traversal mechanics. I did not feel motivated enough to do much of the post game beyond an additional search for eggs before looking a few things up and deciding that no, as a matter of fact I do not want to do all of that.</p>
			
			<p>I feel bad coming across so negatively about <em>Animal Well</em> as I do think it’s a lovely game but <em>La-Mulana</em> might have changed my life. I’m already 20 hours into <em>La-Mulana 2</em> and, assuming all it does is commit less sins than the first game, it’s primed to be one of my all time favorite games.</p>
			]]>
		</content>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<title>Blade Chimera is stuck in the past</title>
		<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.thomasohashi.com/blog/blade-chimera-is-stuck-in-the-past.html"/>
		<id>https://www.thomasohashi.com/blog/blade-chimera-is-stuck-in-the-past.html</id>
		<published>2025-02-05T17:31:34+00:00</published>
		<updated>2025-02-05T10:16:40-08:00</updated>
		<content type="html">
			<![CDATA[
			<p>Metroidvanias are, almost by definition, a derivative genre. Their DNA can be traced back to two games, <em>Super Metroid</em> and <em>Castlevania: Symphony of the Night</em>, and the formula is fairly simple. There’s a big map but you will need to find various items and upgrades to fully explore it.</p>
			
			<p>Most metroidvanias differentiate themselves by expanding on some element like combat (<em>Hollow Knight</em>), movement (<em>Ori</em>), and in some cases, even puzzles (<em>Animal Well</em>). <em>Blade Chimera</em> basically doesn’t do this, to the extent that I am inclined to say its subgenre is actually just “vania,” or perhaps more specifically, <em>Symphony of the Night</em>. All three of Team Ladybug’s metroidvanias are similar in this regard, but while <em>Blade Chimera</em> is the most polished it might be the least innovative.</p>
			
			<p>The long white haired protagonist Shin’s smooth flowy movement — emphasized by his smooth flowy animation — is peak Alucard, right down to the shadow trails on his dodge. The primary gimmick <em>Blade Chimera</em> is a floating sword companion — another nod to Alucard — and though Shin’s is more central to the story of the game, they even share a blue-green color scheme.</p>
			
			<p>Overall it feels great to play, and aside from one particularly dull section, I devoured the game and had a lot of fun with it. Each movement mechanic is extremely well considered, and if you use them creatively you can do some light sequence breaking, which I always appreciate. The ranged weapons were also a highlight and maybe the only thing that really felt fresh. I wish they leaned into them more.</p>
			
			<p>Unfortunately, when I start to think about it relative to the source of its inspiration, it seems lacking. I get it Team Ladybug. I too adore <em>Symphony of the Night</em>, and I am generally happy to play things that evoke it, but when I ask myself if I would have been better off replaying it instead of <em>Blade Chimera</em> the answer is an uncomfortable “probably.” There’s no great twist, the weapon diversity is decent but unremarkable, and Shin as far less charismatic than Alucard.</p>
			
			<p>Team Ladybug is presumably a small team with far less resources than Konami had, much of which must be devoted to visuals, so to some degree this makes sense. I do think it is possible that they will eventually produce something that surpasses Iga’s classic work, but I am also afraid that they are a little too content to live in its shadow, whether out of respect or for lack of imagination.</p>
			
			<p>I still genuinely do recommend this game as it is gorgeous and extremely playable, but if you’ve never experienced <em>Symphony of the Night</em> you should consider doing that instead.</p>
			]]>
		</content>
	</entry>
</feed>