<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<title>thomas ohashi / blog</title>
	<id>https://www.thomasohashi.com/</id>
	<link rel="self" href="https://www.thomasohashi.com/blog/feed.atom"/>
	<link rel="alternate" href="https://www.thomasohashi.com"/>
	<updated>2025-01-20T10:51:36-08:00</updated>
	<author>
		<name>Thomas Ohashi</name>
	</author>
	<entry>
		<title>Blade Chimera is stuck in the past</title>
		<author>
			<name>Thomas Ohashi</name>
		</author>
		<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.thomasohashi.com/blog/blade-chimera-is-stuck-in-the-past.html"/>
		<id>tag:thomasohashi.com,2025-01-20:/blog/blade-chimera-is-stuck-in-the-past.html</id>
		<updated>2025-01-20T10:51:36-08:00</updated>
		<published>2025-01-20T10:51:36-08:00</published>
		<content type="html">
			&lt;p&gt;Metroidvanias are, almost by definition, a derivative genre. Their DNA can be traced back to two games, &lt;em&gt;Super Metroid&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Castlevania: Symphony of the Night&lt;/em&gt;, and the formula is fairly simple. There&rsquo;s a big map but you will need to find various items and upgrades to fully explore it.&lt;/p&gt;
			
			&lt;p&gt;Most metroidvanias differentiate themselves by expanding on some element like combat (&lt;em&gt;Hollow Knight&lt;/em&gt;), movement (&lt;em&gt;Ori&lt;/em&gt;), and in some cases, even puzzles (&lt;em&gt;Animal Well&lt;/em&gt;). &lt;em&gt;Blade Chimera&lt;/em&gt; basically doesn&rsquo;t do this, to the extent that I am inclined to say its subgenre is actually just &ldquo;vania,&rdquo; or perhaps more specifically, &lt;em&gt;Symphony of the Night&lt;/em&gt;. All three of Team Ladybug&rsquo;s metroidvanias are similar in this regard, but while &lt;em&gt;Blade Chimera&lt;/em&gt; is the most polished it might be the least innovative.&lt;/p&gt;
			
			&lt;p&gt;The long white haired protagonist Shin&rsquo;s smooth flowy movement &mdash; emphasized by his smooth flowy animation &mdash; is peak Alucard, right down to the shadow trails on his dodge. The primary gimmick &lt;em&gt;Blade Chimera&lt;/em&gt; is a floating sword companion &mdash; another nod to Alucard &mdash; and though Shin&rsquo;s is more central to the story of the game, they even share a blue-green color scheme.&lt;/p&gt;
			
			&lt;p&gt;Overall it feels great to play, and aside from one particularly dull section, I devoured the game and had a lot of fun with it. Each movement mechanic is extremely well considered, and if you use them creatively you can do some light sequence breaking, which I always appreciate. The ranged weapons were also a highlight and maybe the only thing that really felt fresh. I wish they leaned into them more.&lt;/p&gt;
			
			&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, when I start to think about it relative to the source of its inspiration, it seems lacking. I get it Team Ladybug. I too adore &lt;em&gt;Symphony of the Night&lt;/em&gt;, and I am generally happy to play things that evoke it, but when I ask myself if I would have been better off replaying it instead of &lt;em&gt;Blade Chimera&lt;/em&gt; the answer is an uncomfortable &ldquo;probably.&rdquo; There&rsquo;s no great twist, the weapon diversity is decent but unremarkable, and Shin as far less charismatic than Alucard.&lt;/p&gt;
			
			&lt;p&gt;Team Ladybug is presumably a small team with far less resources than Konami had, much of which must be devoted to visuals, so to some degree this makes sense. I do think it is possible that they will eventually produce something that surpasses Iga&rsquo;s classic work, but I am also afraid that they are a little too content to live in its shadow, whether out of respect or for lack of imagination.&lt;/p&gt;
			
			&lt;p&gt;I still genuinely do recommend this game as it is gorgeous and extremely playable, but if you&rsquo;ve never experienced &lt;em&gt;Symphony of the Night&lt;/em&gt; you should consider doing that instead.&lt;/p&gt;
		</content>
	</entry>
</feed>